Okay, alright. בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Alright, so we today's דף *daf*
is נ *nun*, 50. We pick up at the bottom of מ"ט
עמוד ב' *mem tet amud bet*, and the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. And
now we move from all these interesting questions about a dead fetus
right, the firstborn, into the actually the מצוה *mitzvah* itself of פדיון
*pidyon*. It's not unlike גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s very often or משניות *Mishnayos*
orders where they start with more sort of side issues, although this
really did start directly by defining what the definition of firstborn is
and then dealt with some curious examples and now it's turning to
the מצוה *mitzvah* of פדיון *pidyon* and to defining the five שקל
shekel, *shekel*. Yes, five שקל shekel, *shekel*.
Somebody's poor and don't have,
so then somebody can give it to him as a gift, a
כהן kohen, *Kohen* can even give it to him as a gift
and he can give it back to the כהן *Kohen*. So, you
know. Alright. Let's take a look now at the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*.
We're going to talk today exactly about that, about how much it
was in coins and we'll talk a little bit about how that
translates nowadays. So the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* says the following on the
bottom of מ"ט עמוד ב' *mem tet amud bet*. חמש סלעים של
בן Chamish Selaim shel Ben *chamesh sela'im shel ben*, the five סלע
sela. *sela*. Notice immediately right there's a translation of שקל shekel, *shekel*
to סלע sela *sela*. שקל shekel *shekel* in the תורה Torah *Torah*
is a silver שקל shekel *shekel*, עשרים גרה השקל esrim gera hashekel,
*esrim gerah hashekel* is understood here to be the same as what
was referred to as the סלע sela *sela*. במנה צורי Tzuri. *bemaneh
Tzuri* is measured by the סלעים *sela'im* that were in the Tyrian...
Tyrenian... how do you pronounce the adjective of Tyre?
Tyrian, Tyrian, anyway,
Tyrian מנה maneh. *maneh*. Okay, so in that coinage, there was a
סלע sela *sela* in that coinage and apparently it's a term that
could have been used for other coinages as well, so for the
one that was used in צורי *Tzuri*.
Now, שלושים של עבד *sheloshim shel eved*, the thirty...
the תורה Torah *Torah* says that you pay שלושים כסף kesef, *sheloshim
kesef* when if an ox gores a slave. So there's two assumptions
here: number one is when the תורה Torah *Torah* says כסף kesef,
*kesef* without telling you what type of silver coinage it means the
שקל shekel *shekel*, the silver שקל shekel, *shekel*. Okay, so the standard
כסף kesef, *kesef* in the תורה Torah *Torah*, as we're going to
say at the end of today's דף *daf*, refers to the שקל
shekel, *shekel* and the שקל shekel, *shekel*, which is the סלע sela,
*sela* as determined by this, you know, as was equivalent to this
במנה צורי *bemaneh Tzuri* in the במנה צורי *bemaneh Tzuri* coinage. Okay,
so where are we? שלושים של עבד וחמישים של אונס ומפתה *sheloshim
shel eved vechamishim shel ones u'mefateh*, the fifty שקל shekel *shekel*... כסף
kesef, *kesef* that are paid for the case of rape or seduction
that are paid to the girl's father. So that is also שקל
shekel. *shekel*, silver שקל shekel *shekel* and based on this במנה צורי
*bemaneh Tzuri*. ומאה של מוציא שם רע *u'me'ah shel motzi shem ra*,
the hundred כסף kesef *kesef* paid by the man who marries a
woman and then libels her and claims that she was not a
virgin and then is found to have lied, he pays a hundred
כסף kesef *kesef*, double the normal amount, the fifty כסף kesef *kesef*
that normally was paid at the for the bridal price or for
the כתובה Ketubah, *ketubah*. So that is also this silver שקל shekel
*shekel*. Okay, so that's... כולם בשקל הקודש *kulam beshekel hakodesh*, they are
all in the שקל shekel הקודש *shekel hakodesh*. You know the תורה
Torah *Torah* says, עשרים גרה השקל esrim gerah ha-shekel. *esrim gerah hashekel*,
you know when it speaks about giving the שקל shekel *shekel*, the
half of the שקל shekel, *shekel* to the משכן *Mishkan*, right, חצי
השקל בשקל הקודש עשרים גרה gerah, השקל *chatzi hashekel beshekel hakodesh esrim
gerah hashekel*, מחצית השקל בשקל הקודש עשרים גרה gerah השקל *machatzit hashekel
beshekel hakodesh esrim gerah hashekel*. So all of that, the holy, the
שקל shekel *shekel* used in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*,
that silver שקל shekel. *shekel*, which is twenty גרה gera. *gerah*, and
we'll talk in a minute about what גרה gera. *gerah* means. That
is the same that is being referred to when the תורה Torah
*Torah* just says כסף Kesef, סתם Stam *kesef stam*. It means this
שקל shekel *shekel* and that is equivalent... that is the same as
the סלע sela, *sela* used in this מנה צורי Maneh Tzuri *maneh
Tzuri*. Okay. Now of course none of that helps us if we
don't have any frame of reference for ourselves. That's all just within
other frames of reference, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will try to
translate it into its frame of reference. כולם ניתנין בכסף ובשוה כסף
Kesef. *kulam nitnin bekesef u'veshaveh kesef*, you don't actually have to use
silver per se, you can use even things that are of equivalent
value, חוץ משקלים *chutz mishkalim* or ממחצית השקל *michatzi shekel*. The actual
half שקל shekel *shekel* that you would pay would have to actually
be not in שוה כסף Kesef *shaveh kesef* but in actual silver,
although we will talk about that when we get to the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* about that, okay. So that is the basic point to
הלכה halachic *halachah*. Number one is how much is the coinage, when
the תורה Torah, *Torah* refers to כסף Kesef? *kesef* it means the
שקל shekel *shekel*, which is the same as this סלע sela *sela*.
And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to try to translate
what that סלע sela, *sela* means, whereas and the other question is
that you don't have to pay in actual the coinage itself or
silver, you can even pay in equivalent. So we'll talk about how
all this translates nowadays to פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen, *pidyon haben*, but
first let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay, so
let's take a look. Now, מנה צורי Maneh Tzuri *maneh Tzuri*, what
is this מנה צורי Maneh Tzuri. *maneh Tzuri*? אמר רב אסי מנה
maneh של צורי *Amar Rav Asi maneh shel Tzuri*. Okay, which what...
that helps. That helps, right? But it helps because he's contrasting it
to other opinions. He basically says yes, there was a מנה maneh
*maneh* now. One of the things you have to see here is,
okay, now I want to point out this is an equivalency I've
done for you. One סלע sela. *sela* is four דינר dinar. *dinar*.
Another thing that there's... there's also gold דינרים dinarim *dinarim*, okay, but
we're talking all within silver, okay. So one סלע sela is four
דינר. dinar דינר dinar is also called a זוז, zuz, okay? And
then there's מנה. maneh We're going to get to this later. That's
going to be the גרה, gera although we said 20 גרה gerah.
is 20—we'll talk about that. Anyway, all the way down here to
768 פרוטות, prutot, which are copper. So if you want to know
how much a פרוטה pruta is, remember the debate about בית הלל
Beit Hillel and בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, how much do you need
for קידושי אישה? Kiddushin Isha? Is it one דינר dinar or one
פרוטה? pruta? There's a huge difference, okay? It's about a 1 to
200 ratio, 1 to 196 ratio, a דינר dinar, to a פרוטה,
pruta, okay? So a פרוטה pruta is you know 1/768th of a
סלע.
sela סלע sela, equals a שקל, shekel right?
And five of these are going to be used for פדיון הבן,
Pidyon HaBen? okay? So that's that. Now a מנה maneh is 25
סלעות. selas. So when we say a סלע sela and the מנה
צורי—no, Maneh Tzuri what's a סלע sela, and
25 מנה maneh is what you mean?
One—no, a מנה maneh is 1/25th—yeah, 1/25th of a מנה maneh is
the סלע, sela? right. So a מנה maneh equals 25 סלע, sela,
okay? So when we say a מנה צורי Maneh Tzuri, now, how
many זוז zuz is that? 25 סלע sela. is 100 זוז. zuz.
So very often you know that the גמרא Gemara refers to a
מנה maneh as 100 זוז. zuz.
How is it that I get 24 מנה maneh there and 25
מנה—and maneh 1/25th here?
What? One מנה maneh. is 25 סלע, sela, so 1/25th of a
מנה maneh is one סלע.
sela
But here we have 24
מנה—oh, maneh yeah, I'm sorry. This is—I'm sorry, מעה. ma'ah. מעה, ma'ah,
thank you. Good catch. Okay, that's מעה, ma'ah, not מנה. maneh Okay.
Oh, oh, okay. Anyway, okay, so anyway, sometimes you'll hear that a
מנה maneh is 100 זוז. zuz. It's because מנה maneh is 25
סלע sela. and one סלע sela, is four זוז—four zuz דינר, dinar?
okay. Anyway, so anyway we are saying that the סלע, sela the
סלע sela. is in the מנה צורי. Maneh Tzuri There was a
מנה maneh צורי that was 25
סלעות. selas. 1/25th of that—that is what we're referring to. A מנה
maneh is 25 סלע, Sela.
right?
What? You said a מנה maneh is 25 סלע? Sela. Yes. Why
do you write 1/25th?
Well, 1/25th of a מנה Maneh, equals one
סלע, Sela.
okay?
Brrr. Okay, did we have any—like I'm trying to—So we're going to
talk about—right, I will get to the—okay, you want me to give
you the translation right now? I will give you the translation,
okay.
Generally what we assume based
on the
חזון איש—okay, Chazon Ish the ראשונים Rishonim say that this is equal
to 385 barleys—barley measures. There actually was a measure,
a שקל, shekel שעורים saorim of barley seeds, okay, which was a
pretty precise measure that they used to measure you know precious metal.
Okay, the question is how does it translate now? Most people go
by the חזון איש Chazon Ish who translates it to be roughly
19.2 grams of silver, which would be how much? Okay, which times
5 for the five שקלים—שקל, equals 100 and—what is
it? 196—let's see—50—not 196—it's 96. 15—no, 96. 96 grams, 95.85. 96 grams,
which I am told is roughly
about—about $125.
Well, like
for a כתובה, Ketubah
let's say
200—we'll get to כתובה ketubah later, okay, because there's a question how
do you measure. So $125—so roughly one שקל shekel. is roughly $25,
roughly. Okay, so if you want to know the 50 שקל shekel
for the case of raping the girl, that would be what would
that be? About
$450—not much. Right, is that right? 50 times—no, 50 times
25—four times 25 is 100. 125—1,250.
1,250. 1,250,
okay. 1,250.
How much is a פרוטה pruta by the way for קידושי אישה?
Kiddushin Isha? You divide this by—I can't even do this—divide that by
800. What's $25 divided by 800?
Three something. No.
Hold on.
300—35,000—where's my calculator here?
25 divided by 800 is—I
can't find my lousy calculator on this phone. Anyway, 25 divided by
100 is
250—is $2.50,
and divided by 8, $2.50 is what, 30 cents?
Something—$2.50 divided by 10 is 2—yeah, it's about 30 cents. No, not
30 cents, right? No, 30 cents. 30—it's about 30 cents. So one
פרוטה pruta is about 30 cents if you want to know. Oh,
okay.
שווה פרוטה, shaveh pruta, okay.
I think I did the math right, because if you multiply that
by a thousand, which is close to a thousand, you'll get 30
cents—you'll get—by 100 is 30—no, no, no, no, not 30 cents—3 cents,
right? Because you multiply it by a thousand then you'll get right,
30 cents—3—yeah, 3 cents a פרוטה, pruta, roughly. Okay, yes.
The question is
we're talking about $125,
but today— What did he just
say?
Like, and this is what I'm trying to understand. Like let's say
then they used, I'm for argument's sake, like a שקל shekel. was
let's say a dollar coin, just for argument's sake, right? So then
you use today whatever your dollar coin is.
No, the תורה Torah always talks about, they assume the תורה Torah
doesn't just mean coins, the תורה Torah? means a particular amount of
weight of silver. Right, but why do we assume that? I don't
know, that's what they... Okay, so there's a basic, that's just a
tacit assumption. No, they just take it for granted.
Yeah, I just looked up,
especially in a, one minute, especially in a time when, one second,
especially in a time when you did not have, all of your
money was actual, what do you call it, was actual, it wasn't,
it was intrinsic value. It wasn't like now, our money is not
intrinsic value. So if the תורה Torah is giving an amount of
money based on intrinsic value, let's, it's as if the תורה Torah
said like, you know, five, it's as if the תורה Torah, said
five ounces of silver. So of course you assume that that means
whatever that equivalence is.
Yes, with the new price, with the higher price of silver, there's
96 grams are around $70, $75 today.
96 grams, $75? Yeah, you said $125.
You're
saying, yeah, the 96 grams, I just calculated, it's about $75 today.
It's less. Yeah, but three years ago it was about a quarter
of that.
Really? Oh yeah. Okay. So, all right, so I don't know where
I got the 125 number from.
Maybe 1980 when the price was even higher.
That could be.
Because it fluctuates all over the place. So
96 grams is about two and a half troy ounces.
Are we sure, wait a minute, are we sure the same, are
we talking about the same, is there like grams and troy grams
or is it only ounces and troy ounces?
No, so a gram, so there are 454 grams in a pound
and there are 12 troy ounces in a pound. So 96 grams
is about two and a half troy ounces. Okay. And silver yesterday
is about $29 a troy ounce.
Okay. All right, there you go. I have to double check where
I got
the dollar equivalence from. So how many זוז zuz is in
a, 200 זוז, zuz,
well for כתובה ketubah you mean? Okay, so we're going to talk,
let's hold off because we are going to come up to כתובה
Ketubah, and I want to talk about it because it could be
a major fluctuation based on how you do this rate of exchange.
I know, but I will get there, just hold off.
Last year because the price of silver had gone up, Rabbi Willig
had Mr. Brown had to bring much more, many more coins than
he had to bring.
Interesting. Okay. Rabbi, Mr.
Brown buys the חמץ chametz for most of New York through Rabbi
Willig, and Rabbi Willig had him bring more silver coins than he
usually used to have to bring.
He buys the what?
He buys the
חמץ. chametz. חמץ? chametz? To buy חמץ. chametz. Okay.
Moving on.
Moving on. Okay, so that's the first explanation did not really translate,
it just said we're using this מעה ma'ah Tyrian, which was what
the משנה Mishna, said. Now,
I don't know. I don't know. רבי אמר, Rabbi amar, רבי Rabbi
says, רבי אמי אמר, Rabbi Ami amar, דינרא ערבאה, dinara arvah, an
Arabian dinar. Now רש"י Rashi has an explanation with this which I
will spare you because it's complicated. I'm going to read this like
תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot basically says now we are comparing it to
the gold דינרי dinari and actually what תוספות Tosafot says we are
doing, and this actually answers Michael's question as well, is we're not
just saying what is the ratio here. What תוספות Tosafot says we
are doing is if you have to bring,
well actually let's keep that there, okay, a מנה is 25 סלע.
Sela? Okay, now if you have to bring five
שקל, shekel right, one minute, let me see if I got this
right. Okay, yes, if you have to bring five סלע, Sela. five
שקל, shekel right, that is how many דינר? dinar, That's 20 דינר,
dinar. right? Right?
So your five
שקל, shekel שקל/סלע is going to be 20 דינר. dinar, Yes, is
that clear based on the equivalency here?
So תוספות Tosafot says that this explanation here, an Arabian dinar, is
that what that would actually, hold on, let me just double check
תוספות Tosafot one more second, hold on.
One minute.
Yes, so תוספות Tosafot says
that and I'm
sorry, I'm sorry, I'm just processing this. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot actually
says that remember we had before, I'm sorry, I had this all
in my head. So go slower, okay. All right, all right, anyway,
anyway, remember we also said
that a what do you call it, a מנה is
25 סלע. Sela, So תוספות Tosafot says a מנה is essentially the
same here as certain types of דינר, dinar. so the explanation that
an Arabian dinar that we just read, an Arabian dinar, or the
explanation that the... Michael, which said מנה צורי, we're not, we're talking
about how much is the total of the five שקל. shekel, What
is five שקל shekel. is what תוספות Tosafot says we're saying? Not
what coinage are we using. We want to give a bottom line,
what is the five שקל shekel for פדיון הבן? Pidyon HaBen? So
five שקל shekel is in this standard coinage, but we're trying to
translate it into the גמרא's Gemara other coinage. In this standard coinage,
the five שקל shekel is twenty דינר. dinar. Okay, what was that,
got that? This twenty דינר. dinar. What was that in their coinage?
So it was some number around twenty, but they didn't have an
exactly equal coinage. So the first explanation was מנה צורי was... so
the first explanation was, forget... well let's look at the first explanation
of the Arabian דינר. dinar תוספות Tosafot says an Arabian
דינר dinar was equal to twenty-five of those זוז, zuz, twenty-five by
twenty. Arabian דינר dinar, was equal to twenty-five of those
זוז. zuz.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, it's just that the terms switch
because wait a minute, כלומר דינר של ערבא שוה ה סלעים, kolmar
dinar shel arva shaveh hei sela'im, one minute. One minute,
one minute, one minute.
Sure. Why am I looking at the Steinsaltz? I have this at
home.
Yeah, I know, I have this at home. Is that the Steinsaltz
box in the building? The forty million dollars and cents, it says,
it's so much
easier.
Is that for this?
There's...
okay, so okay, okay, okay, okay, okay, I figured it out. I
figured out what I was talking about.
Sorry, sorry. Here's what I was doing wrong. Okay, what's missing from
this is the gold equivalent, okay, the gold equivalent. So one, normally
we say,
here's the point. Normally we say one דינר, dinar, silver דינר, dinar
oops.
Normally we say like this: one gold דינר dinar.
equals twenty-five silver דינר.
dinar Okay, that's the key. Okay, this is the key. One gold
דינר dinar. equals twenty-five silver דינר. dinar. Now,
we need to bring how many דינרים dinarim. for the שקל, shekel
for the פדיון הבן? Pidyon HaBen Five שקל shekel. is twenty דינרים.
dinarim Yes? Okay, so for פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen, it is twenty,
twenty silver דינר. dinar
All right, now, twenty silver דינר dinar. is a little less than
one gold דינר. dinar Yes? But תוספות Tosafot says some other coinages
were a little different than the standard. So the first answer here
of... of דינר ערבאה, dinar arva'ah, that actually one gold Arabian דינר
dinar. actually did equal twenty silver דינר. dinar. So that all you
needed for the פדיון הבן, Pidyon HaBen. this was one gold Arabian
דינר. dinar Normally one דינר dinar would have been too much, but
one gold Arabian דינר dinar, actually gave you exactly what you wanted.
That was the first opinion.
That was the first century?
Whatever, I don't know whatever רבי אמי Rabbi Ami was.
Okay, this is רבי אמי.
Rabbi Ami. Okay, so this is the point. We're talking about gold
coinage. So we know you need twenty-five silver דינר, dinar רבי אמי
Rabbi Ami is saying one Arabian דינר dinar, is essentially the same.
Okay, that's point number one.
רבי חנינא אומר איסטירא סרסירא, Rabbi Chanina omer istira sarsira, a Syrian
איסטירא. istira. Now, so what תוספות Tosafot says that this, now what
is a Syrian איסטירא? istira? דמזדבנא תמניא בדינרא, demizdabna tamanya bedinara,
that normally eight of them go for a דינר, dinar. חמש מנייהו
לפדיון הבן, chamesh minaihu le-Pidyon HaBen,
five of them for a פדיון הבן. Pidyon HaBen. Which means what?
If you
have... so he's basically saying is you have five-eighths of a Syrian
דינר. dinar, So listen to what he said. He said eight of
these דינר, dinar. right? So one-eighth of eight, he said דמזדבנא תמניא
בדינרא. demizdabna tamanya bedinara. So this איסטירא, istira, okay, there is eight
איסטירא, istiras, Syrian איסטירא, istiras, for one gold דינר. dinar Okay, one
gold דינר dinar, says דמזדבנא תמניא באסירא, demizdabna tamanya ba-asira, eight of
these איסטירא istiras for one gold דינר, dinar. five of these איסטירא,
istiras, so basically five of these will work for פדיון הבן. Pidyon
HaBen. So what does that mean? That means five-eighths of a gold
Syrian איסטירא, istira, is that clear? One
איסטירא istira equals
one-eighth of a gold דינר. dinar This is in Syrian coinage. Yes?
Right? Because eight of them equals one, one of them equals one-eighth.
Five איסטירא istiras will get you your פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. So
five-eighths of a gold Syrian איסטירא. istira. star will get you your
twenty silver. So, according to him, this gold Syrian איסטר istar tells
us that the math is essentially
thirty-two, not twenty-five. So five-eighths of thirty-two will get you twenty. Okay,
so they're doing it in their coinage, meaning in a standard coinage
they would say one דינר dinar is too much, you need like
four-fifths of a דינר dinar for פדיון הבן. pidyon haben Comes along
the רשב"ם Rashbam and says, oh, one gold Arabian דינר dinar is
exactly right. Comes along the other one and says you could also
do five-eighths of a Syrian דינר dinar. which has more gold in
it, right? It's bigger, and that'll also get you your twenty, your
twenty. Okay, so all of these are...
yeah, what?
Well, they used to take five איסטרין. istarin. Yeah, you'd actually...
no, but that's his point, you could take five איסטרין istarin because
an איסטר istar is an eighth of it.
Okay, so they're all translating according to תוספות, Tosafot, what is going
to get you your פדיון הבן pidyon haben. money? Okay, in the
standard coinage it would be four-fifths of a gold דינר. dinar The
first opinion says yeah, but that's essentially...
they're all agreeing according to תוספות, Tosafot, so that's great.
That's essentially one Arabian דינר dinar is what... the other says the
Syrian דינרים dinarim are bigger, so if you wanted to do Syrian
דינרים or איסטרין istarin
which are an eighth of it, you'd use five-eighths of a Syrian
דינר dinar and you'd get your twenty.
So essentially רש"י's Rashi value is a fifth of that of תוספות.
Tosafot. What רש"י... Rashi... what one of them is, תוספות Tosafot is
saying what all of them are.
I'm not going to talk about רש"י Rashi right now.
Okay, so five silver dollars?
Yes, but the question is do those silver dollars have to have
enough actual value in terms of silver value? You've got enough to
ritualize it with five silver dollars?
Right, because there's some coins that aren't all silver.
Right, they're not silver coins.
Okay, let's read a little bit more. Okay, so top of נו
עמוד א', nun amud aleph, top right here. רבי יוחנן אומר, Rabbi
Yochanan omer, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says דינרא הדרינא טיירינא שייפא dinra
hadreina tayreina sheifa דמזדבנא בעשרין וחמש
זוזי. demizdabna be'esrin vechamish zuzei.
Okay, now רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying a Hadrianic... רש"י Rashi
says it's Hadrian, תוספות Tosafot says it actually just means circular or
whatever. Hadrianic, Tyrian שייפא, sheifa, רש"י Rashi says it's the name of
some Roman governor or king or whatever. Could just mean whatever. Anyway,
some type of Roman דינר dinar, דמזדבנא בעשרין וחמש זוזי. demizdabna be'esrin
vechamish zuzei.
Now this is the exact... this is the standard, right? Which I've
been telling you. One standard דינר, dinar twenty-five silver. Okay, a דינר
dinar is a silver דינר dinar is also a זוז. zuz. Okay,
so he starts talking about this. This is our standard one. So
now that's not going to be... that's going to be too much,
right? He says one of these Tyrian Hadrianic דינר dinar. which goes
for twenty-five זוזי. zuzei. Twenty-five זוזי zuzei is the same as twenty-five
silver דינר. dinar. Okay, well that's too much, what you really need
is four-fifths of that, right?
So זוז zuz equals one silver דינר.
dinar Okay, רבקה, Rivka, we're not forgetting about כתובה, Kesuva we're getting
back to that. Okay, now how are you going to get there?
How are you going to go down? We would say take four-fifths
of it. So the גמרא Gemara will get there but in somewhat
of a roundabout way. So let's take a look. דל מינייהו שתותא,
dal mineihu shetuta, remove a sixth. Right, okay, now a sixth is...
we would have said a fifth. Okay, a sixth of twenty-five is
four and change, right? Four times six is twenty-four. Take away a
sixth והנך לפדיון הבן, vehanach lepidyon haben, what's left is for פדיון
הבן. pidyon haben? So the גמרא Gemara says what do you mean?
הני עשרין וחד נכי דנקא הוו. hanei esrin vechad nechi danka havei.
That's twenty-one minus a sixth, right? I'm not going to do the
whole math but you see that it's a little less than twenty-one,
right? Because a sixth of twenty-five is four and change. So the
גמרא Gemara says that's a little less than twenty-one, that's not twenty.
אלא דל שתותא וזוזא, ela dal shetuta vezuza,
take away a sixth, so you get a little less than twenty-one
and then take away one. But then you're a little less than
twenty. That's too little. והנך לפדיון הבן. vehanach lepidyon haben. So the
גמרא Gemara says אכתי עשרין נכי דנקא הוו, achti esrin nechi danka
havei, it's still twenty minus a sixth, it's too little. אלא דל
זוזא, ela dal zuza, fine, first take away the זוז, zuz, then
you get yourself down to twenty-four, ושתותא, veshetuta, then remove a sixth
of twenty-four which gets you down to twenty. והנך לפדיון הבן vehanach
lepidyon haben דהוו להו עשרין dehavei lehu esrin מתקלי במתקלי דדינרא. metkali
bemetkali dedinra. Twenty זוז zuz in the weight of דינר dinar, דאינון
עשרין. de'innun esrin. Now, before we get to the דאינון de'innun state.
Okay, so that's how you get from here what he basically is
saying is four-fifths of this. Okay, four-fifths of that, of a דינר,
dinar of a standard דינר dinar. equals, right, it would equal twenty
זוזי, zuzei, twenty silver דינר. dinar, Okay, so now anyway, the funny
thing is, by the way, it proves that the גמרא Gemara likes
the idea of a sixth. Because a sixth is a... you know,
because we would have just said take a fifth off, right? The
גמרא Gemara says minus one and then take a sixth. But anyway,
this is your sort of standard and that's what's finally being used
here. In this standard one gold דינר, dinar how much is פדיון
הבן? pidyon ha-ben Four-fifths of it. But if you want to do
it in others, it's either one Arabian דינר dinar gets you it
straight, or five-eighths of a Syrian דינר dinar. and you'd get your
twenty. Okay, so anyway here we're dealing with the four-fifths of the
standard. Okay, so let's keep on going. Now the גמרא Gemara translates
this.
רש"י Rashi says this next line might be a gloss. And here's
how the גמרא Gemara now translates it because into maybe more contemporary
currency: דאינון עשרין ותמניא. de'innun esrin v'tamnya.
which is equivalent to in another currency, although we now said it's
twenty זוז, zuz, in a slightly different currency it's equal to twenty-eight
and a half and a half of a sixth. So twenty-eight and
seven-twelfths. So if you want רש״י, Rashi, this twenty זוז zuz is
equal to in some other currency twenty-eight and seven-twelfths זוז. zuz. We're
not going to worry about that. Moving on. Now we've gotten all
the different currencies that are going to get you your five שקל.
shekel? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, סלע דאורייתא, sela d'Oraita, the Torah סלע,
Sela. תלתא ותילתא
הוי tlata v'tilta havei was three and a third זוז. zuz. We've
been assuming it is a one to four ratio. He says the
Torah's שקל shekel, actually was one to three point three. How do
I know? He says why, דכתיב de'chtiv the pasuk says
עשרים גרה gerah
השקל, the שקל shekel, is twenty גרה. gerah ומתרגמינן umitargaminan עשרים מעין,
esrim ma'in, twenty מעה. ma'ah. Okay? ותניא v'tanya שש מעה כסף
דינר, shesh ma'ah kesef dinar, that there are six מעה ma'ah in
a דינר.
dinar So look, what you have here, right, you see here
it's a six to one ratio, דינר dinar, to a מעה. ma'ah.
But the Torah says that a שקל shekel. is twenty גרה. And
if a גרה is a מעה, ma'ah, then you're going to it's
twenty-four. How do we get this to be twenty? So either you
could change this ratio, that the ratio in the Torah maybe was
a one to five ratio. Right, that would get you what you
wanted. But we're going to assume this ratio is fixed. So the
only way you're going to get this to be twenty is if
you say this isn't four, but three and a third. Three and
a third times six will get you twenty. Is that clear? More
or less? Okay. So in the Torah, one equaled twenty, now one
equals twenty-four. So we're saying in the Torah this ratio switched to
be three point three. And then you take three point three times
six, you get twenty.
Plus not the Torah ratio switched, their ratio switched.
Right, in the Torah it was three point three and then the
ratio switched later. Okay.
So now the גמרא's Gemara going to we've measured the measurements. Well,
yeah, so the גמרא's Gemara going to say that.
Okay. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on this, אבל סלע של קודש
ארבעים ושמונה פונדיון. aval sela shel kodesh arbaim u'shmonah pundiun. So פונדיון
זה מעה וקילבון לפרוטות. pundiun zeh ma'ah u'kilbon l'prutot.
So now what the Torah says like this, the Torah says that
if you, you know, sell a field during the period of the
יובל, Yovel, then you have this opportunity or you מקידש makdish a
field, excuse me, then you have an opportunity to buy it back
but you do it based on the amount of years to the
יובל. Yovel. And it says that if there's a full forty-nine years
to the יובל, Yovel, then it says that you what one minute,
right, so fifty שקל shekel. is for this
field בית זרע חומר שעורים. beit zera chomer se'orim. So for a
certain type of a barley field, fifty שקל shekel for the forty-nine
years to the יובל. Yovel. Now divide that out by forty-nine. How
much is that per year? So fifty divided by forty-nine, the first
forty-nine are easy, it's one שקל. shekel, One שקל shekel, per year
plus, right, one forty-ninth of a of a שקל. shekel Now each
you get that? If you've got to get that's forty-nine times something
to get fifty, it's forty-nine times one and one forty-ninth.
Now actually, it's not bad because a פונדיון pundiun here, you have
forty-eight of them.
So if you do one שקל shekel, and a פונדיון pundiun and
you multiply it by forty-nine, then at the end of the fifty
years, the forty-nine years, you're going to have fifty שקל shekel, and
a leftover פונדיון. pundiun. You see that? Forty-nine times one שקל shekel
gives you forty-nine שקל, shekel, and forty-nine times one פונדיון pundiun will
give you forty-nine פונדיון, pundiun, which is one שקל. shekel So you
will get fifty שקל shekel, and a leftover פונדיון. pundiun. So therefore
when we figure out how much if you have to redeem a
field, if it's fifty שקל shekel. for the forty-nine years, how much
is each year come to? It's one שקל shekel and a פונדיון,
pundiun, a tiny bit less than a
פונדיון. pundiun. So this משנה Mishna, asks the following. It says
or this ברייתא, braita, might be in ספרא. Sifra. Anyway, it asks
the following. It says
this ברייתא, braita, שש מעה, shesh ma'ah, but אבל סלע של קודש
ארבעים ושמונה פונדיון, aval sela shel kodesh arbaim u'shmonah pundiun, but it's
only forty-eight פונדיון. pundiun. פונדיון זה מעה, pundiun zeh ma'ah, what about
the leftover? It's not an accurate, it's pretty darn close, but it's
not totally accurate. You have one leftover פונדיון. pundiun. So it's really
not exactly one and one, you know, one שקל shekel. and one
פונדיון. pundiun. So it says קילבון לפרוטות. kilbon l'prutot. So fine, that's
like a rounding error. Okay. That in order that it's not always
exact, it may be the amount of money that you need in
order to change the coinage, whatever it is. That's not our issue.
טיבום לפרוטות. tivum le-prutrot. רש״י Rashi says it means that it's some
type of a rounding for the specific amounts, meaning all the little
specifics, you lose something in the process, meaning if you, you know,
when you weigh out again, we're talking about precious metals, not about
representative values, so you need a little bit there for rounding. Anyway,
so what's our problem? Our problem is that we're saying in the
תורה, Torah, it actually does work like this and it is actually
48, right? If you're saying it's 20 here, so it would only
be 40, not 48. So you see we're working, we're talking about
the תורה's Torah 50 שקל.
shekel. So we're talking that we do have this ratio. How do
you say that this really is 20? That would make that a
40.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. So it says בתר
דאוספו עלייהו. basar de-osfu aleihu. No,
obviously they changed this after the תורה Torah was written, the coinage
changed. Okay. And therefore and and it became, it did become one
to four, not one to 3.3, which meant 24, which meant 48.
Now, of course you'll say, but who cares if the coinage changed?
Shouldn't we be defined by how much that value was at the
time of the תורה? Torah, So we're going to see that חז״ל
Chazal understood that the תורה Torah would allow, this somewhat goes to
Michael's question about are we restricted exactly by the amount of silver,
are we defined by what our contemporary coinage is? So the גמרא
Gemara understood some middle position. You don't just go by dollars or
whatever your contemporary coinage is, but if you're using essentially the same
coinage and it's essentially silver coins with roughly the same amount, a
certain amount of variation about how much silver and how big the
coin is would be accepted and would be incorporated into the system.
Okay. And that's what we're saying. After they after they made the
coins bigger. דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, עשרים גרה
השקל. It's 20 גרה. למדנו לשקל שהוא עשרים גרה. lamadnu le-shekel she-hu
esrim gerah. Okay. מניין שאם רצה להוסיף יוסיף? minayin she-im ratzah le-hosif
yosif? How do you know that you can increase the amount of
גרה weights to a שקל? shekel תלמוד לומר יהיה. talmud lomar yihyeh.
שיהיה, she-yihyeh, which means I guess
regardless. עשרים גרה יהיה
השקל.
esrim
gerah yihyeh ha-shekel. Okay.
Okay. יהיה, yihyeh, you would think means it's fixed, but somehow יהיה
yihyeh is understood to mean it's an extra word to mean like
whatever you make it. יכול יפחות? yachol yifchos? Maybe you could even
make it less silver? תלמוד לומר הוא. talmud lomar hu. Okay. So
עשרים גרה הוא. esrim gerah hu. So הוא hu means that there's
a bottom. Okay. So now what we have is like this.
Nowadays, yes,
there's three דינר, dinar, three silver דינר, dinar, there's four silver דינר,
dinar which makes 24, which makes 48, and that becomes incorporated into
the system. But at the time of the תורה Torah actually, שקלים
shekalim were smaller and it was only 3.3 and it was only
20 all the way down. So if you were dealing with, if
you did not accept the change of coinage and you said I'm
going to be an originalist, I'm going to go by the weight
of coinage at the time of the תורה, Torah you would actually
wind up giving less for פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen. because your סלע
Sela. was actually not a full four דינר dinar. but only 3.3
דינר. dinar. It was smaller. And now we're going to see a
story about that where somebody actually decided I'm not going by the
new coinage, I'm going by the old one, save myself a little
money. Yes.
Who's creating these coins?
The larger government.
Secular, no, you know, I don't know, the secular, not the Jewish
government.
That's the reason why they're ridiculous.
Well, why they're ridiculous? In the תורה, Torah the תורה Torah said
גרה and שקל, shekel. whatever, they weren't minting their own coins.
They didn't say because if it were, if it were created by
a religious government, all the coins would be very easy to figure
out. Right. This and that. Right, right.
But
we do have some coins from the בר כוכבא Bar Kochba period.
Okay. That's, yeah.
That was only a few years.
Yeah. Okay. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Now we have an interesting story. רב אשי שדריה שיתסר זוזי לרב
אחא בריה דרב אינא
בפדיון הבן. Rav Ashi shadrei shitsar zuzei le-Rav Acha brei de-Rav Ina
be-pidyon ha-ben. So רב אשי Rav Ashi had his firstborn son and
he sent and רב אחא בריה דרב אינא Rav Acha brei de-Rav
Ina was a כהן, so he gave him 17 זוז. zuz. Now
if you've been paying attention, you'll know it should have been 20
זוז, zuz, right? That's our, okay. Now, שלח ליה, shalach lei, he
sent him, לישדר לי מר תלתא אחריני דאיכא עלייהו. lishdar lei mar
tlata achrinei de-ika aleihu.
Hey, give me the other three זוז zuz you owe me. Okay.
You only paid me 17 זוז. zuz. שלח ליה, shalach lei, he
sent back to him, לישדר לי מר תילתא אחרינא דאוסיפי עלייהו. lishdar
lei mar tilta achrina de-osifi aleihu. Give me back the extra third
that I gave you. What does he mean? He's saying, I don't
go by this fancy new four דינר.
dinar, I'm a, I go by the old 3.3.
If
you go by the old three and a third דינר, Dinar, so
times five is going to get you not 20 but anybody do
the math? 15 and five-thirds is 16 and two-thirds. So I sent
you 17, give me back the third you owe me. You want
the three extra, you're going by the four which is times five
is 20, you want the three extra, I'm going by the old
three and a third. So give me back, I gave you 17,
I only owe you 16 and two-thirds, give me back the third
you owe me. Okay.
So we don't, however, that was a nice לומדות lomdus about him,
but we generally assume that we use the new
coinage. Now the גמרא Gemara says יוסי? Yosie? And we don't know
what happened. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר
רבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Chanina כל כסף אמור בתורה סתם סלע. kol
kesef amur batorah stam sela. That's what we've been assuming. When the
תורה Torah says כסף, Kesef it means שקל, shekel, which is what
we call a סלע. Sela. That's what we've been assuming. דנביאים, Dinevi'im,
when it says כסף, Kesef which just means silver coinage, it doesn't
tell us which, so he for some reason assumes that when it's
in the נביאים, Nevi'im, it refers to a ליטרין, litrin, a liter,
which is whatever ליטרין litrin is, which רש"י Rashi says is, let
me just double check רש"י, Rashi,
which is twenty-five שקל. shekel. So when in the נביאים Nevi'im it
says כסף, Kesef, it's referring to a twenty-five times larger coin. דכתובים,
Dikesuvim, when it says it in כתובים, Kesuvim, that's קינטרין, kintrin, which
is a hundred שקל. shekel So when it's using the same number,
it's like, you know, something had said, you know, it's like Israel,
like the new שקל shekel, or the old שקל, shekel. right? Was
it a hundred times or ten times? It was ten times. There
was times when they had devalued their currency, whatever they did, a
hundred times translation. So anyway, he says כסף, Kesef whatever the standard
coinage is, although it's not שקל, shekel he's not saying that's what
שקל shekel. means. כסף Kesef. just means silver coinage. What was the
assumed standard they were using? The תורה, Torah the standard was שקל,
shekel, whereas in the נביאים, Nevi'im, it was a silver coin that
was twenty-five times as large, and in the כתובים, Kesuvim, a silver
coin that was a hundred times as large. חוץ מכספו של עפרון,
Chutz mikaspo shel Ephron, the one exception is when אברהם Avraham bought
the field from עפרון, Ephron, because this fits into חז"ל's Chazal general
approach, you know, that עפרון Ephron was אמור הרבה ועשה מעט, emor
harbeh va'aseh me'at, he spoke like, oh, keep it, keep it, and
then he demanded a very, very high price. So it says four
hundred שקל, shekel. דכתיב, dechsiv, ארבע מאות שקל כסף עובר לסוחר, arba
me'os shekel kesef over lasocher, although it just says בתורה סתם, batorah
stam, although it just says כסף Kesef. or שקל shekel there, it
actually says שקל, shekel קינטרין, kintrin, it really is the type of
שקל Shekel. or the type of, although it does say שקל, Shekel,
that's a hundred שקל. Shekel, דכתיב, Dechsiv, how do you know? ארבע
מאות שקל כסף עובר לסוחר, arba me'os shekel kesef over lasocher, four
hundred שקל Shekel. of silver that would be, you know, would be
acceptable currency anywhere. ואיכא דוכתא דקרו לקינטרא תקלא, Ve'ika duchsah d'karu l'kintra
tikla, and there are places where they call this קינטרא, kintra,
a שקל. Shekel. Meaning, until now we've just been saying כסף Kesef
means a קינטא, kinta, but he actually says there are some places
where they call it a שקל. Shekel. So he's choosing to read
when it says שקל Shekel, that's accepted everywhere, he means any place
would acknowledge that this is considered a שקל. Shekel, So the places
where they call a קינטר kintar a שקל, Shekel, it would have
to be a hundred שקלים shekalim to be called a שקל. Shekel
Are you getting me? Meaning, he's reading the פסוק pasuk where it
says four hundred שקל Shekel accepted anywhere, what that probably just means
is like, you know, pure silver that anybody would acknowledge, you know,
you wouldn't have to weigh it out or whatever, but he's interpreting
it to mean in any place it would be called a שקל,
Shekel, where there's some places they only call what we call a
hundred שקלים, shkalim they would only call that a שקל. Shekel, So
if it's called a שקל shekel everywhere, it must be the actual
קינטר kintar which is worth a hundred שקל. So rather than אברהם
Avraham paying four hundred שקל, אברהם Avraham actually paid forty thousand שקל.
Okay, so there's... that's a very... well,
forty thousand, if we're saying a שקל is about twenty-five dollars, forty
thousand is four is a hundred, so it's a hundred thousand dollars.
Not bad, considering where, you know, Manhattan real estate prices are today.
Okay, yeah. But the bigger problem is coins hadn't been invented yet
in אברהם אבינו's Avraham Avinu time. Oh, really?
I think you had mentioned that somewhere before. So שקל there would
have just meant a weight, a weight, and עובר לסוחר over lasocher
would have probably been like some stamped weight, so it would have
been acknowledged that this was pure and this was weighed what it
said it weighed or something. That's a nice point. Okay, anyway, moving
on. אמר רב יאשיה, Amar Rav Yoshiya, ביקשו לגנוז כל כסף וזהב.
bikshu lignoz kol kesef vezahav. Now
this is actually a סוגיא sugya in עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, we're
just importing it here because we're talking about silver and gold. ביקשו
לגנוז כל כסף וזהב שבעולם מפני כספה וזהבה של ירושלים. Bikshu lignoz
kol kesef vezahav sheba'olam mipnei kaspah vezahavah shel Yerushalayim. They wanted to
forbid using any gold and silver in the world because once ירושלים
Yerushalayim was destroyed, there was all that gold and silver that was
in the temple treasuries and then it got dispersed. So maybe any
gold and silver that you're using comes from the temple treasuries and
it's מעילה. me'ilah. So they wanted to say you couldn't do it.
Okay, of course the גמרא Gemara is going to say that's a
pretty far-fetched concern, so we'll see in a minute. But עד שמצאו
לו מקרא מן התורה, ad shematzu lo mikra min hatorah, they found
a פסוק pasuk שהוא מותר, shehu mutar, שנאמר, shenemar, that made it
permissible, ובאו בה פריצים וחיללוה, uvo ba'u pritzim vechillaluha, that when the,
when the, you know, non-Jews, the פריצים, pritzim, actually means those that
violated, the violators came in, they desecrated it, they secularized it. And
from there we actually learn, they profaned it, thank you. From there
we actually learn a principle that when, and this actually has interesting
הלכה halachic implications, like times when like שולן shuls were taken over
by the Nazis and by non-Jews and by Christians, what is the
status of what was there, does it lose its קדושה, kedushah, you
know, and so on. So actually they learn that when the בית
המקדש was destroyed, the things that had been sanctified actually became desacralized.
That actually leads to the חנוכה Chanukah story, that having to resanctify,
you know, so exactly what the הלכה parameters of that are we're
not going to go into, but they're saying because of that, the
gold and silver in the treasuries lost their קדושה kedushah and we
didn't have to worry about it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
just says what was the הוה אמינא. hava amina. So the גמרא
Gemara says בירושלים... biYerushalayim... דרובא דעלמא *d'ruba d'alma* ירושלים *Yerushalayim* is the
majority of the world? So, there was some gold and silver there,
we were going to make it forbidden in the entire world? אלא
אמר אביי ביקשו לגנוז דינרא הדרינא טיירנא שייפא *Ela amar Abaye bikshu
lignoz dinra hadrayna teyrana sheyafa*. Remember that's what we mentioned before, those
Tyrian, Hadrianic coinage, those are ones that were very
specific and that were dominant in the treasure houses in the בית
המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. So those are the ones that we wanted to
forbid because there was a greater likelihood that some of those came
from the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. Okay, מפני טיבעה של ירושלים *mipnei
tivah shel Yerushalayim* because of the coins in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* that were
sanctified. עד שמצאו לו מקרא מן התורה *ad shematzu lo mikra min
haTorah* until they found the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* שבו נדרש שנאמר ובאו
בה פריצים וחיללוה *shebo nidrash shene'emar uva'u vah paritzim vechillaluha*. So that
was a תנא *Tanna* to just refer to this coinages, this coins
that we had mentioned before. Yes.
Hadrian and Trajan ruled after the destruction.
Oh, you're right. Trajan, that's what טריאנא *Triana* is. Okay, thank you.
Wait a minute, right, that's right, so the Hadrianic persecutions were רבי
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. Yes. That's an interesting point.
Maybe it means like the same type of coinages, you know, in
their time they were calling it Hadrianic, but maybe it was, you
know, of a similar of a similar genre and
they were stamped with Hadrian or Trajan's face on it.
You would know that it wasn't. That's a good point. Unless they
had remelted it and reused it. Okay, oy, Charlie, you're making us,
you're bringing in facts.
All right, now, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אסי Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Rav Assi, *amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Assi*. Now we're getting
to the issue that Rivka wanted to talk about. כל כסף Kesef
האמור בתורה סתם כסף Stam Kesef צורי *kol kesef ha'amur baTorah stam
kesef Tzori*. That's what we've been saying before. Whenever the תורה Torah
*Torah* just says כסף Kesef *kesef*, it means this Tyrian כסף Kesef
*kesef*, which is שקל *shekel*, okay, which is this whole ratio that
we've been talking about. ושל דבריהם ve-shel Divreihem *veshel divreihem*, but when
the rabbis use the word כסף Kesef. *kesef* in rabbinic מצוות *mitzvos*
or obligations or whatever, כסף מדינה Kesef Medinah *kesef medinah* is the
is the sort of, you know, more sort of local כסף Kesef,
*kesef*. The local כסף Kesef, *kesef* was one-eighth of the Tyrian כסף
Kesef *kesef*. So it's a big difference whenever it says you owe
200 שקל *shekel* or whatever כסף Kesef *kesef* or זוז Zuz? *zuz*
as we're going to talk about in a minute, Rivka, the question
is going to be are we talking about biblical, which is this
ratio, or are we talking about rabbinic, which is one-eighth, where the
values are one-eighth of what they are according to this ratio. So
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says כללא הוא *klala hu*? Is this
really a rule? והרי תניא דכתיב Dechsiv, *ve-harei tanya de-chtiv* when it
says that if you claim that somebody, you know, owes you money
and he says he only he doesn't owe you the whole amount
and he admits a part of this, he takes an oath. So
the question is how big of a claim is needed to to
obligate somebody in an oath? So the verse says כי יתן איש
אל רעהו כסף Kesef או כלים Kelim *ki yiten ish el re'ehu
kesef o kelim*. If you give to your friend silver, money, or
vessels לשמור *lishmor* and then he denies part of it or he
denies it, he takes an oath. So how much did you give
him to for a claim to be able to demand an oath?
ותנן U'tnan, *u-tenan* we taught in the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*, שבועת הדיינים
*shvuat hadayanim* when it comes to the oath imposed by in the
courts, הטענה שתי כסף Kesef *hata'ana shtei kesef* the claim have to
the original claim has to be for two כסף Kesef, *kesef*. Now
two כסף Kesef *kesef* we understand to mean, now this is based
on a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in the תורה Torah, *Torah*, but we
understand that that's actually שתי מעות *shtei ma'ot*. And it's not by
the laws way down there on the list, right? And it is
and it's not the two כסף kesef *kesef*. If it were the
two כסף *kesef* in the תורה Torah *Torah*, it would be 48
מעה *ma'ah*. Are you with me? The תורה Torah. *Torah* says כסף
*kesef*, if it was the כסף *kesef* in the תורה *Torah*, right,
it would be if it was one it would be 24 מעה
*ma'ah*, if it was two it would be 48. But now how
do we know but this שתי כסף *shtei kesef*, I mean now
here it's not exactly clear what the question is because it just
says שתי כסף *shtei kesef*. But if you look at רש"י Rashi
*Rashi*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says שוה שתי מעות *shaveh shtei ma'ot*. It's
two מעות *ma'ot*. Okay, so somehow we knew we know the context
here is שתי מעות *shtei ma'ot*. So that's not the כסף האמור
בתורה *kesef ha'amur baTorah*. כסף האמור בתורה *kesef ha'amur baTorah* would give
you 24 מעה *ma'ah* or if you doubled it 48. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says שאני התם דכתיב כסף או כלים *shani hatam
de-chtiv kesef o kelim*. It's because it's linked to vessels. מה כלים
שנים Shnayim, אף כסף שנים *ma kelim shnayim af kesef shnayim*. So
and now of course it's funny, okay, so they tell you you
need two. ומה כסף דבר חשוב אף כלים דבר חשוב *u-ma kesef
davar chashuv af kelim davar chashuv*. And the same way money is
important, so vessels are important. So how did that answer the question?
So רש"י *Rashi* actually says that it's not really about כלים *kelim*
being two, but about כלים *kelim* being מה שהם *ma shehem*. Since
כלים *kelim* don't have, you know, even any small vessel, כלים *kelim*
doesn't have any particular value assigned to it, it could be even
something trivial, so the כסף *kesef* here could also be something trivial.
So that's the way רש"י *Rashi* reads the סוגיא *sugya* that the
problem is we're talking about מעה *ma'ah*, we should have been talking
about
סלע Sela, *sela*. You could read the סוגיא *sugya* differently. You could
read that the question was just why do we say two? Why
not say one? And the answer is because it says כלים *kelim*.
כלים *kelim* is two, so כסף *kesef* is two. That would be
a much easier way to read this. But רש"י *Rashi* is reading
it that he assumed that we're talking way down here about מעות
*ma'ot*, why aren't we talking way up here about סלע Sela, *sela*?
And the answer is, well, because כלים *kelim* can mean even low-priced
כלים *kelim*. כלים *kelim* is doesn't have to refer to a high
value, so therefore the כסף *kesef* also we assume it's further down
the list. If you want to see different ways of learning
the
סוגיא *sugya*, this then it
wouldn't even come before the court. What? If it's a case
of... No, it would come before
the court, but it would not be able to entail an oath,
a שבועה. Shvuah A שבועה Shvuah, of מודה במקצת Modeh B'miktzas requires
טענה. Ta'anah.
So even if I gave you שמונה פרוטות, Shmonah Prutos, it still
wouldn't be... right, for a שבועה, correct. But it still comes to
the court. Right. So anyway, for a minimum court case then?
No, I think even for a פרוטה. Prutah. Now רש"י actually says
explicitly, like his גירסא, Girsa, he interprets the גירסא Girsa that the
point here is not the שנים, the point here is כלים כלשהן.
Kelim Kolshein. But that's not even in our גירסא. Girsa. But כלים
suggests even low value, and therefore we're talking about a low value
כסף, not a high, not a standard כסף. That's the way רש"י
would say it. Okay, moving on. תרי מעשר, Trei Maaser, how about
פדיון מעשר? Pidyon Maaser? דכתיב, the פסוק says וצרת הכסף בידך, V'tzarta
Hakesef B'yadecha, you should bind the כסף in your hand when you
redeem מעשר. Maaser. And we're saying סתם כסף is a שקל. Okay.
ותנן, U'tnan, הפורט סלע ממעות מעשר שני Haporeit Sela Mimaos Maaser Sheni
or something, so if you go, or ממעות מעשר שני, Mimaos Maaser
Sheni, so it talks about if you redeemed your מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni on small coins and now you want to exchange it for
larger coins, how you do the exchange. But the key is that
you initially exchanged them on coins that were less than a שקל,
less than a סלע. Sela. Now you're coming to exchange them for
a סלע. Sela How do we let you do that if the
תורה says you redeem it on כסף? And we're saying כסף means
a סלע. Sela How do we allow you to redeem it on
less than a סלע? Sela So the גמרא Gemara says, no, what
does it say?
So כסף כסף ריבה. Kesef Kesef Ribah. It says כסף twice, ולקחת
הכסף, V'lakachta Hakesef, וצרת הכסף, V'tzarta Hakesef, which means any type of
silver coin. So it's not limited just to the big one, the
סלע. Sela. Okay. והרי הקדש, V'harei Hekdesh, דכתיב ונתן הכסף וקם לו,
Dechsiv V'nasan Hakesef V'kam Lo, that talks about redeeming things that are
sanctified and you give the money, and again כסף, so you would
think you need to redeem it only on a סלע, Sela? only
on a large coin. ואמר שמואל, V'amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel says הקדש
שווה מנה שחיללו על
שווה פרוטה מחולל. Hekdesh Shaveh Maneh Shechilalo Al Shaveh Prutah Mechulal. You
can even, if you redeemed, it's not allowed to, but if you
redeemed הקדש Hekdesh worth a מנה, right, as we know is a
hundred, you know, whatever, remember before, it's like thousands of פרוטה, Prutah,
even if you redeemed it on one פרוטה, Prutah, it works. So
you see though, the point here is that you can redeem it
on a copper פרוטה, Prutah, you don't need to redeem it on
a whole סלע. Sela? Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says הקדש נמי
ילפינן קודש קודש ממעשר. Hekdesh Nami Yalfinan Kodesh Kodesh Mimaaser.
We learn it from מעשר Maaser the same way מעשר Maaser wasn't
limited to a large כסף coin, הקדש Hekdesh also is not limited.
Okay. והרי קידושי אישה, V'harei Kiddushei Isha, how about marrying a woman?
דכתיב ויצאה חינם אין כסף. Dechsiv V'yatza Chinam Ein Kesef. This is
about when a father sells his daughter as a slave and then
she goes free, and says she goes free without money. ותנן, U'tnan,
and we learn from there that's one of the sources that a
woman is married with כסף. That here there's no money paid, but
if the father marries his daughter, then the person gives money to
the father. So the point about bringing that in is that according
to one version, we learn the idea that a woman is married
with money from a verse that says כסף. So according to what
you're saying, that should be only limited to a סלע. Sela. ותנן,
and no, בית שמאי אומרים בדינר ובשווה דינר, Beis Shammai Omrim B'dinar
U'vshaveh Dinar, בית הלל אומרים בפרוטה ובשווה פרוטה. Beis Hillel Omrim B'prutah
U'vshaveh Prutah. So בית הלל Beis Hillel says all the way down
to a פרוטה Prutah you can do קידושי אישה, Kiddushei Isha, you
don't need to be way up at the top of the list.
So and you're saying that כסף means a סלע. Sela לימא רב
אסי דאמר כבית שמאי? Leima Rav Assi D'amar K'veis Shammai? So is
he really going like בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? Even בית שמאי Beis
Shammai says a דינר, Dinar. right? If we're saying that כסף means
a סלע, Sela, we're actually before דינר. Dinar. So even בית שמאי
Beis Shammai doesn't say that the כסף in the תורה for קידושי
אישה Kiddushei Isha means a סלע, Sela that would be four דינר.
Dinar But it's pretty close. Okay, that's why there's a big תוספות
Tosfos because there's problems reading this גמרא Gemara because, you know, why
does the גמרא Gemara think a דינר Dinar. would
work if כסף means a שקל, it should have been four דינר.
But anyway, certainly at least he's close to בית שמאי. Beis Shammai.
So what are you doing with all these things? None of these
things demand a שקל. So the גמרא Gemara. says אלא אי איתמר
הכי איתמר. Ela Ei Ismar Hachi Ismar. Here's a better way of
saying it. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אסי, כל כסף קצוב האמור
בתורה כסף צורי. Kol Kesef Katzuv Ha'amur Batorah Kesef Tzori. We're not
saying when the תורה just says סתם money, כסף. If the תורה
says you redeem on money, you marry a woman with money, you
sell with money, it means money, whatever the money is, there's no
particular amount. But if it gives you an amount, if it puts
a dollar price to it, if it says that the slave is
gored, you pay thirty כסף, it says that for the case of
rape
and seduction it's fifty כסף, it gives a price value, then we
have to know what the word כסף means, and that means שקל.
So you understand this is a major shift. It's not saying כסף
as a generic money means שקל. כסף as a generic means money,
whatever the money is, you can redeem on anything, you can redeem
מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, you can redeem הקדש, Hekdesh, קידושי אישה Kiddushei
Isha is up for חז"ל Chazal to figure out how much it
means, that's... Generic, when it gives a specific amount, 50 שקל, 30
שקל, whatever, 5 שקל, that is referring to the סלע. Sela Okay?
And that basically brings us back to our משנה. Mishna Okay, כסף
קצוב בתורה כסף צורי, Kesef Katzuv baTorah Kesef Tzuri, ושל דבריהם ve-shel
Divreihem. when it's a rabbinic amount, כסף מדינה is local סלע Sela,
which is 1/8. So גמרא says מאי קמשמע לן Mai kamashmalan what
are you teaching us? תנינא Tanina we taught in our משנה, Mishna.
חמש סלעים של בן etc., etc., is כסף צורי Kesef Tzuri ושל
דבריהם כסף מדינה. ve-shel Divreihem Kesef Medinah. It says explicitly that the
amounts in the תורה are כסף צורי Kesef Tzuri and the rabbinic
amounts are this local סלע Sela which is an eighth. So the
גמרא says איצטריך ושל דבריהם כסף מדינה איצטריך ליה. Itztreich ve-shel Divreihem
Kesef Medinah itztreich lei. I'm sorry, I put the wrong emphasis, because
our משנה, Mishna right? Our משנה Mishna. doesn't say ושל דבריהם. Our
משנה Mishna just says what the תורה's שקל is. So it says,
why do you need this, it's in our משנה. Mishna Our משנה
Mishna says that the תורה's שקל is this סלע מדינה—is Sela Medinah
this סלע צורי. Sela Tzuri. So it says, no, you're right, we
know that the תורה's is this צורי. His חידוש Chidush is that
the rabbinic one is 1/8 of that. ושל דבריהם כסף מדינה איצטריך
ליה. ve-shel Divreihem Kesef Medinah itztreich lei. When the—what he—his חידוש Chidush
was was when in rabbinic obligations, it is the local סלע Sela
which is an eighth. דתנן D'tnan and here's an example: התוקע לחברו
נותן לו סלע. Ha-tokeia l'chavero notein lo sela. It says that if
somebody basically either like, you know, like claps somebody on the ear,
okay it doesn't make him deaf but it's obviously, you know, maybe,
you know, gives him a certain momentary embarrassment or you know and
so on, or you know makes him a momentarily ringing in the
ear, he has to pay him a סלע. sela Okay, that was
a fine, a fixed fine that they had established. So how much
is a סלע? sela Is it going to be four זוז? Zuz
Is it going to be, you know, is it that סלע? So
it says ולא תימא סלע ארבע זוזי. ve-lo teima sela arba zuzei.
No, so we're not talking about the biblical סלע. This is a
rabbinic—this is a rabbinic teaching. It's not an amount in the תורה,
it's an amount in the משנה. So don't say we mean four
זוז Zuz but we're talking about the local, and the local is
1/8. So what's 1/8 of four? 1/8 of four?
Half. Four-eighths is a half. So don't say that that משנה means
four זוז Zuz. and the סלע is the biblical
סלע, אלא פלגא דזוזא. ela palga de-zuza. We mean a half זוז.
Zuz. דקרי אינשי סלע פלגא דזוזא D'kari inshi sela palga de-zuza because
yes, there is a local value currency where a סלע is a
half זוז. Zuz So basically, yes, it's—our משנה is clear that the
biblical when it gives a price tag and says כסף or שקל,
it means this סלע based on this thing we have. But when
there's a price amount, a specific amount in the משנה or a
ברייתא, Baraisa, a rabbinic specific amount, we're dealing with and we use
סלע, we're dealing with a local currency which is 1/8. It's a
huge difference. Now we're going to have a story and then I'm
going to get back to Rivka's question about the כתובה Kesuva. which
is very relevant. So let's take a look. חנן בישא, Chanan Bisha,
so this guy חנן בישא, Chanan Bisha, you've got to love that
name which is like "the bad Chanan", תקע ליה ההוא גברא, taka
lei hahu gavra, he did this, he clapped this guy on the
ear, whatever it was. אתא לקמיה דרב הונא, Ata l'kamie d'Rav Huna,
came to רב הונא. Rav Huna. אמר ליה הבו ליה פלגא דזוזא,
Amar lei havu lei palga de-zuza, give him a half זוז Zuz.
because this is an illustration, a סלע means a local סלע which
is a half זוז. Zuz Okay, so it says הוה ליה זוזא
מאיכס, hava lei zuza me'ichas, so he had a זוז Zuz, which
was like worn away, the face of it away or whatever,
בהדיה דלא נפיק, bahadei d'lo nafik, that people wouldn't accept, it was
like, you know, it was—you know, it was one of those sort
of worn away coins that nobody wanted to take. Now it was
a זוז, Zuz. he only owed the guy a half זוז. Zuz.
So what did he do? So תקע ליה אחרינא ויהיב ליה. taka
lei achrina ve-yahiv lei. He gave him another clap on the ear
and he gave him the זוז. zuz. That was his solution to
that problem, which is very lovely. Anyway, the גמרא clearly isn't endorsing
that, but I—you probably won't forget that story. So now here is
the key question about כתובה. Kesuva? How much is a כתובה? Kesuva
So כתובה Kesuva, is 50 כסף,
okay, 50 שקל, which is 10 times the פדיון הבן. pidyon haben.
So it's basically if you accept
this, although Charlie tells us it's 75, but if you accept this
let's say it's around 100, so that would make it basically 1,000,
the value of a כתובה, Kesuva $1,000. However, there's a debate in
the גמרא whether כתובה Kesuva is biblical or rabbinic, and whether we
really learn it out from where it says 50 כסף in the
תורה or is it a completely rabbinic. And some—now the גמרא doesn't
say what I'm about to say. The גמרא just has "does it
originate"—actually that's not true.
שמעון בן שטח, Shimon ben Shatach, actually what I—I strike that. Anyway,
there's some question about how to—the implications of that in the גמרא.
Anyway, according to a—you know, a number of ראשונים, Rishonim, if it's
rabbinic, then you have to do an eighth of that, and an
eighth of that gets it down from $1,000, which itself isn't so
much, like 100—$125. Okay, or whatever it is. So that is a
very—now some ראשונים Rishonim say, for example, in the language of the
כתובה Kesuva we say דחזי ליכי מדאורייתא, d'chazi lichi mid'oraisa, that are
deserving to you from the תורה. But now some ראשונים Rishonim ask,
don't we rule that a כתובה Kesubah is מדרבנן? miderabbanan? So some
ראשונים Rishonim actually say yes. כתובה Kesubah is דרבנן, derabanan, but we
still figure out the value based on the fifty כסף in the
Torah. That what the רבנן rabanan are saying is, first of all,
it's in זוז. zuz. It's in זוז. zuz, And here we're just
saying that the סלע is an eighth. Right, and I actually wanted
to check that because it might be that there was a coin
called a סלע which was a סלע מדינה sela medina which was
an eighth, but we never said that the word זוז, zuz there
was a זוז zuz. that was an eighth of the standard זוז.
zuz. And the standard amount in חז"ל Chazal is always 200 זוז.
zuz. So essentially some ראשונים Rishonim say that yes, it might be
rabbinically obligated, not biblically obligated, but it's based on the פסוק in
the Torah. And therefore when we say דחזי ליכי מדאורייתא, dechazi lichi
mide'oraisa, what we mean is based on the biblical fifty שקל which
is the 200 זוז. zuz, But we're not cutting it by an
eighth. But there are definitely some ראשונים Rishonim that want to argue
that it should be an eighth of this, but but yes, the
standard assumption is that even if it's rabbinic, it's based on the
biblical amount. And I think you're right, זוז, zuz I don't think
there are two types of זוז zuz out there. And therefore it's
this. Now even a thousand dollars is not a lot, even if
you don't cut it by an eighth.
But nobody says today a thousand, they range. I recently asked
about this. Yeah, I asked a בית דין Beis Din once
because I was going to ask something. What what did they tell
you?
Well, I asked how much is it worth, they didn't answer me,
but she got up and she said, I want to know how
much money I'm waiving. Right. And they got very disturbed and quiet
and whispering and then we were insisting, so finally this one rabbi
said anywhere from four thousand dollars to forty thousand dollars.
So let me tell you let me tell you why. Let me
tell you why. The כתובה Kesubah amount, even if you don't divide
by an eighth, which is generally assumed you don't, is still just
like not too much more than a thousand dollars. It's like I
said, it's ten times פדיון הבן. So where does it come from?
Because in the in the Middle Ages, I don't remember the exact
century, 12th maybe earlier maybe later, anyway, they realized that they really
did use the כתובה Kesubah as a real financial document to ensure
that the woman had, you know, what you know was provided for.
I understand, but they also realized that the that the standard amount
of 200 זוז zuz. was not going to help her too much.
So if you know our standard כתובה Kesubah says, it's not just
the 200 זוז. zuz. What does our standard כתובה Kesubah say?
זוזי מאתן דחזי ליכי מדאורייתא. zuzi masan dechazi lichi mide'oraisa.
But before you get to the תוספת, tosefes, first we have a
fixed amount that we value the dowry at regardless of what the
dowry was, right? And it says, you know, it says
what's the exact line there? It says ונדוניא דהנעלת ליה מבי אבוה
בין בכסף בין בדהב בין בתכשיטין במאני דלבושא בשימושי דירה ובשימושי ערסא
הכל קיבל עליו חתן דנן במאה זקוקים כסף צרוף. v'nadunya d'han'alas lei
mibei avuha bein b'chesef bein b'dahav bein b'tachshitin b'manei d'levusha b'shimushi dira
u'v'shimushi arsa hakol kibel alav chasan denan b'me'ah zekukim kesef tzaruf.
So there he says that we this idea to have a fixed
valuation of the dowry, which would be what he would have to
pay her back even if she brought in nothing, at a hundred
זקוק zakok of pure silver. A זקוק zakok was much bigger than
a זוז. zuz, And then his תוספת tosefes that he gives מידיליה
midilei is another זקוק. zakok. So 200 זקוק zakok is don't be
confused, it's not 200 זוז, zuz. it's much much more than 200
זוז. zuz, So the actual value of the כתובה Kesubah is very
little, the 200 זוז, zuz which is maybe a thousand dollars, and
the primary value which was instituted by אשכנזים Ashkenazim in the Middle
Ages was to add this 200 זקוק zakok and that's where there's
four thousand to forty thousand. But anyway, a זקוק zakok of silver
is much much larger than a זוז zuz. and that's where the
real value of the כתובה lies, not in the 200 זוז. Okay,
so we'll end with that.
Good for us to know. Of course, they never know.
And that's why when you get a divorce 30 years ago.